chapter 3.
There was music from my neighbor's house through the summer nights. In his blue
gardens men and girls came and went like moths among the whisperings and the
champagne and the stars.
At high tide in the afternoon I watched his guests diving from the tower of his
raft, or taking the sun on the hot sand of his beach while his two motorboats
slit the waters of the Sound, drawing aquaplanes over cataracts of foam.
On weekends his Rolls-Royce became an omnibus, bearing parties to and from the
city between nine in the morning and long past midnight,
while his station wagon scampered like a brisk yellow bug to meet all trains. And
on Mondays eight servants, including an extra gardener, toiled all day with mops
and scrubbing brushes and hammers and garden shears repairing the ravages of the night before.
Every Friday five crates of oranges and lemons arrived from a fruit here in New
York— —every Monday these same oranges and lemons left his back door in a pyramid
of pulpless haves There was a machine in the kitchen which could extract the
juice of 200 oranges in half an hour if a little button was pressed 200 times by
a butler’s thumb.
At least once a fortnight a core of caterers came down with several hundred
feet of canvas and enough colored lights to make a Christmas tree of Gatsby’s enormous garden.
On buffet tables, garnished with glistening hors d'oeuvres spiced baked
hams crowded against salads of harlequin designs and pastry pigs and turkeys
bewitched to a dark gold.
In the main hall a bar with a real brass rail was set up, and stocked with gins
and liquors and with cordials so long forgotten that most of his female guests
were too young to know one from another.
By seven o’clock the orchestra has arrived, no thin five-piece affair, but a
whole pit full of oboes and trombones and saxophones and vials and cornets and
piccolos, and low and high drums. The last swimmers have come in from the beach now
and are dressing upstairs; the cars from New York are parked five deep in the
drive, and already the halls and salons and verandas are gaudy with primary
colors and hair shorn in strange new ways, and shawls beyond the dreams of
Castile. The bar is in full swing, and floating rounds of cocktails permeate
the garden outside, until the air is alive with chatter and laughter, and
casual innuendo and introductions forgotten on the spot, and enthusiastic
meetings between women who never knew each other’s names. The lights grow
bright earth the earth lurches away from the sun, and now the orchestra is playing
yellow cocktail music, and the opera of voices pitches a key higher laughter's
easier minute by minute, spilled with prodigality, tipped out at a cheerful word.
The groups change more swiftly, swell with new arrivals, dissolve and form in
the same breath; already there are wanderers, confident girls who weave here
and there among the stouder and more stable, become for a sharp, joyous moment
the center of a group, and then, excited with triumph, glide on through the sea
change of faces and voices and color under the constantly changing light.
Suddenly one of the gypsies, in trembling opal sees as a cocktail out of thin air,
dumps it down for courage and, moving her hands like Frisco, dances out alone on
the canvas platform.
A momentary hush; the orchestra leader varies his rhythm obligingly for her, and
there's a burst of chatter as the erroneous news goes around that she is
Gilda Gray’s understudy from the Follies.
The party has begun.
I believe that on the first night I went
to Gatsby’s house I was one of the few guests who had actually been invited.
People were not invited— —they went there.
They got into automobiles which bore them out to Long Island, and somehow they
ended up at Gatsby’s door.
Once there they were introduced by somebody who knew Gatsby, and after that
they conducted themselves according to the rules of behavior associated with
amusement parks Sometimes they came and went without having met Gatsby at all,
came for the party with the simplicity of heart that was its own ticket of admission.
I had actually been invited.
A chauffeur in uniform of robin's egg blue crossed my lawn early that Saturday
morning with a surprisingly formal note from his employer:
the honor would be entirely Gatsby’s, it said, if I would attend his “little party” that night.
He had seen me several times, and had intended to call on me long before,
but a peculiar combination of circumstances had prevented it—
—signed J Gatsby, in a majestic hand.
Dressed up in white flannels I went over to his lawn a little after seven, and
wandered around rather ill at ease among swirls and eddies of people I didn’t know—
—though here and there was a face I had noticed on the commuting train.
I was immediately struck by the number of young Englishmen dotted about; all
well-dressed all looking a little hungry, and all talking in low, earnest voices to
solid and prosperous Americans.
I was sure that they were selling something: bonds or insurance or automobiles. They
were at least agonizingly aware of the easy money in the vicinity and convinced
that it was theirs for a few words in the right key.
As soon as I arrived I made an attempt to find my host, but the two or three
people whom I asked his whereabouts stared at me in such an amazing way, and
denied so vehemently any knowledge of his movements, that I slunk off in the
direction of the cocktail table— —the only place in the garden where a single man
could linger without looking purposeless and alone.
I was on my way to get roaring drunk from sheer embarrassment when Jordan
Baker came out of the house and stood at the head of the marble steps, leaning a
little backward and looking with contemptuous interest down into the garden.
Welcome or not, I found it necessary to attach myself to someone before I should
begin to address cordial remarks to the passersby.
“Hello!” I roared, advancing towards her. My voice seemed unnaturally loud across the garden.
“I thought you might be here,” she responded absently as I came up.
“I remembered you lived next door to—” She held my hand impersonally, as a promise
that she’d take care of me in a minute,
and gave ear to two girls in twin yellow dresses, who stopped at the foot of the steps.
“Hello!” they cried together. “Sorry you didn’t win.” That was for the golf tournament. She had
lost in the finals the week before.
“You don’t know who we are,” said one of
the girls in yellow, “but we met you here about a month ago you dyed your hair
since then,” remarked Jordan, and I started, but the girls had moved casually on and
her remark was addressed to the premature moon, produced like the supper,
no doubt, out of a caterer’s basket. With Jordan’s slender golden arm resting in
mine, we descended the steps and sauntered about the garden.
A tray of cocktails floated at us through the twilight, and we sat down at
a table with the two girls in yellow and three men, each one introduced to us as
Mr. Mumble.
“Do come to these parties often inquire Jordan of the girl beside her. “The last
one was the one I met you at,” answered the girl, in an alert confident voice. She
turned to her companion: “Wasn’t it for you, Lucille?” It was for Lucille II I like
to come,” Lucille said. “I never care what I
do, so I always have a good time. When I
was here last I tore my gown on a chair, and he asked me my name and address—
—inside of a week I got a package from crorers with a new evening gown in it.”
“Did you keep it?” asked Jordan. “Sure I did.
I was going to wear it tonight, but it
was too big in the bust and I had to have it altered. It was gas blue with
lavender beads 265 dollars.” “There’s something funny about a fellow
that’ll do a thing like that,” said the other girl eagerly. “He doesn’t want any
trouble with anybody Who doesn’t?” I inquired. “Gatsby. Somebody
told me—” The two girls in Jordan leaned together confidentially.
“Somebody told me they thought he killed a man once.”
A thrill passed over all of us. The three Mr. Mumbles bent forward and listened eagerly.
“I don’t think it’s so much that argued Lucille skeptically It’s more that he
was a German spy during the war.” One of the men nodded in confirmation.
“I heard that from a man who knew all about him, grew up with him in Germany,” he
assured us positively. “Oh, no,” said the first girl, “it couldn’t be that, because
he was in the American army during the war.” As our credulity switched back to her
she leaned forward with enthusiasm. “You look at him sometimes when he thinks
nobody’s looking at him. I’ll bet he killed a man.” She narrowed her eyes and shivered.
Lucille shivered. We all turned and looked around for Gatsby.
It was testimony to the romantic speculation he inspired that there were
whispers about him from those who found little that it was necessary to whisper
about in this world.
The first supper— —there would be another one after midnight— —was now being served,
and Jordan invited me to join her own party, who were spread around a table on
the other side of the garden.
There were three married couples and Jordan’s escort, a persistent
undergraduate given to violent innuenda and obviously under the impression that
sooner or later Jordan was going to yield him up her person to a greater or lesser degree.
Instead of rambling, this party had preserved a dignified homogeneity, and
assumed to itself the function of representing the staid nobility of the
countryside— —East Egg condescending to West Egg and carefully on guard against
its spectroscopic gaiety.
“Let’s get out whisper Jordan, after a somewhat wasteful and inappropriate half
hour this is much too polite for me.” We got up, and she explained that we were
going to find the host: I had never met him, she said, and it was making me uneasy.
The undergraduate nodded in a cynical, melancholy way. The bar, where we glanced
first, was crowded, but Gatsby was not there. She couldn’t find him from the top
of the steps, and he wasn’t on the veranda.
On a chance we tried an important looking door, and walked into a high
Gothic library paneled with carved English oak, and probably transported
complete from some ruin overseas.
A stout, middle-aged man, with enormous Allied spectacles, was sitting somewhat
drunk on the edge of a great table, staring with unsteady concentration at the shelves of books.
As we entered he wheeled excitedly around and examined Jordan from head to foot.
“What do you think?” he demanded impetuously. “About what?” He waved his hand
toward the bookshelves. “About that. As a matter of fact you needn’t bothered to
ascertain. I ascertained they are real.” “The books?”
He nodded. “Absolutely real— —have pages and everything. I thought they’d be a nice
durable cardboard. Matter of fact, they’re absolutely real Page isn't Here let me show you.”
Taking our skepticism for granted, he rushed to the bookcases and returned
with Volume 1 of the Stoddard Lectures “See!” he cried triumphantly. “It’s a bona
fide piece of printed matter. It fooled me. This fell as a regular Belasco. It’s a
triumph. What thoroughness! What realism!
Knew when to stop, too— —didn’t cut the pages.
But what do you want? What do you expect?” He snatched the book from me and
replaced it hastily on its shelf, muttering that if one brick was removed
the whole library was liable to collapse.
“Who brought you?” he demanded. “Or did you just come? I was brought. Most people were brought.”
Jordan looked at him alertly, cheerfully, without answering.
“I was brought by a woman named Roosevelt,” he continued. “Mrs Claude Roosevelt. Do you
know her? I met her somewhere last night.
I’ve been drunk for about a week now, and
I thought it might sober me up to sit in a library.”
“Has it?” “A little bit, I think. I can’t tell
yet. I’ve only been here an hour. Did I tell you about the books they are real
there You told us.” We shook hands with him gravely and went back outdoors.
There was dancing now on the canvas in the garden; old men pushing young girls
backward in eternal graceless circles, superior couples holding each other
tortuously, fashionably, and keeping in the corners— —and a great number of single
girls dancing individualistically or relieving the orchestra for a moment of
the burden of the banjo or the traps.
By midnight the hilarity had increased. A celebrated tenor had sung an Italian, and
a notorious contra alto had sung in jazz, and between the numbers people were
doing “stunts” all over the garden, while happy evacuous bursts of laughter rose
toward the summer sky.
A pair of stage twins, who turned out to be the girls in yellows did a baby act
in costume, and champagne was served in glasses bigger than finger bowls
The moon had risen higher, and floating in the Sound was a triangle of silver
scales, trembling a little to the stiff tiny drip of the banjos on the lawn.
I was still with Jordan Baker. We were sitting at a table with a man about my
age and a rowdy little girl, who gave way upon the slightest provocation to
uncontrollable laughter.
I was enjoying myself now. I had taken two finger bowls of champagne, and the
scene had changed before my eyes into something significant, elemental, and profound.
At alola in the entertainment the man looked at me and smiled.
“Your face is familiar,” he said politely.
“Weren’t you in the third Division during the war?”
“Why yes. I was in the ninth machine gun battalion I was in the seventh infantry until June
1918.
I knew I’d seen you somewhere before.” We talked for a moment about some wet
gray little villages in France. Evidently he lived in this vicinity, for he told me
that he had just bought a hydroplane, and was going to try it out in the morning.
“Want to go with me, old sport?
Just near the shore along the Sound.” “What time anytime that suits you best.”
It was on the tip of my tongue to ask his name when Jordan looked around and smiled.
“Having a gay time now?” she inquired. “Much better.” I turned again to my new acquaintance.
“This is an unusual party for me. I haven’t even seen the host. I live over there—”
I waved my hand at the invisible hedge in the distance, “and this man Gatsby sent
over his chauffeur with an invitation.” For a moment he looked at me as if he
failed to understand.
“I’m Gatsby,” he said suddenly.
“What!” I exclaimed. “Oh, I beg your pardon.” “I thought you knew, old sport.
I’m afraid I’m not a very good host.” He smiled understandingly— —much more than
understandingly.
It was one of those rare smiles with a quality of eternal reassurance in it,
that you may come across four or five times in life.
It faced— —or seemed to face— —the whole external world for an instant, and then
concentrated on you with an irresistible prejudice in your favor It understood
you just so far as you wanted to be understood, believed in you as you would
like to believe in yourself, and assured you that it had precisely the impression
of you that, at your best, you hoped to convey.
Precisely at that point it vanished— —and I was looking at an elegant young
roughneck, a year or two over 30 whose elaborate formality of speech just missed being absurd
sometime before he introduced himself I got a strong impression that he was
picking his words with care.
Almost at the moment when Mr. Gatsby identified himself a butler hurried
toward him with the information that Chicago was calling him on the wire.
He excused himself with a small bow that included each of us in turn.
“If you want anything just ask for adults board he urged me.
“Excuse me.
I will rejoin you later.” When he was gone I turned immediately to
Jordan— —constrained to assure her of my surprise I'd expected that Mr. Gatsby would be a
florid and corpulent person in his middle years.
“Who is he?” I demanded.
“Do you know?” “He’s just a man named Gatsby.”
“Where is he from, I mean? And what does he do?” “Now yours started on the subject,” she
answered with a wand smile. “Well, he told me once that he was an Oxford man.”
A dim background started to take shape behind him, but at her next remark it faded away.
“However, I don’t believe it.” “Why not?” “I don’t know,” she insisted, “I just don’t
think he went there.” Something in her tone reminded me of the
other girls I think he killed a man,” and had the effect of stimulating my curiosity.
I would have accepted without question the information that Gatsby sprang from
the swamps of Louisiana were from the lower East Side of New York. That was comprehensible.
But young men didn’t— —at least in my provincial experience I believe they
didn’t— —drift coolly out of nowhere and buy a place on Long Island Sound.
“Anyhow, he gives large parties,” said Jordan, changing the subject with an
urbane distaste for the concrete. “And I like large parties. They’re so intimate.
At small parties there isn’t any privacy.” There was the boom of a bass drum, and
the voice of the orchestra leader rang out suddenly above the echolalia of the garden.
“Ladies and gentlemen,” he cried. “At the request of Mr. Gatsby
we're going to play for you Mr Vladimir tostal's latest work, which attracted so
much attention at Carnegie Hall last May.
If you read the papers you know there was a big sensation.”
He smiled with jovial condescension, and added: “Some sensation!” Whereupon everybody
laughed. “The piece is known,” he concluded lustily, “as Vladimir tostov's Jazz
History of the World!’ The nature of Mr tostov's composition eluded me, because
just as it began my eyes fell on Gatsby, standing alone on the marble steps and
looking from one group to another with a proving eyes. His tanned skin was drawn
attractively tight on his face and his short hair looked as though it were
trimmed every day. I could see nothing sinister about him. I wondered if the
fact that he was not drinking helps to set him off from his guests, for it
seemed to me that he grew more correct as the fraternal hilarity increased.
When the “Jazz History of the World” was over, girls were putting their heads on
men’s shoulders in a puppy-ish convivial way, girls were swooning playfully
backward into men’s arms, even into groups, knowing that someone would arrest
their falls— —but no one swooned backward on Gatsby, and no French bob touched
Gatsby’s shoulder, and no singing quartets were formed with Gatsby’s head for one link.
“I beg your pardon Gatsby butler was suddenly standing
beside us. “Miss Baker?” he inquired. “I beg your pardon, but Mr. Gatsby would like to
speak to you alone.” “With me?” she exclaimed and surprised Yes
Madam She got up slowly, raising her eyebrows at me in astonishment, and
followed the butler toward the house.
I noticed that she wore her evening dress all her dresses, like sports clothes—
—there was a jauntingness about her movements as if she had first learned to
walk upon golf courses on clean, crisp mornings.
I was alone and it was almost two.
For some time confused and intriguing sounds had issued from a long many
windowed room which overhung the terrace.
Eluding Jordan’s undergraduate, who is now engaged in an obstetrical
conversation with two chorus girls, and who implored me to join him, I went inside.
The large room was full of people. One of the girls in yellow was playing the
piano, and beside her stood a tall, red-haired young lady from a famous chorus, engaged in song.
She had drunk a quantity of champagne, and during the course of her song she
decided, ineptly, that everything was very, very sad— —she was not only singing, she was weeping
too.
Whenever there was a pause in the song she filled it with gasping, broken sobs,
and then took up the lyric again in a quavering soprano. The tears coursed down
her cheeks— —not freely, however, for when they came into contact with her heavily
beaded eyelashes they assumed an inky color and pursued the rest of their way
in slow black rivulets.
A humorous suggestion was made that she sing the notes on her face, whereupon she
threw up her hands, sank into a chair, and went off into a deep vineous sleep.
“She had a fight with a woman who says he’s her husband,” explained a girl at my
Alba I looked around. Most of the remaining women were now having fights
with men said to be their husbands.
Even Jordan’s party, the quartet from East AG were rent asunder by dissension.
One of the men was talking with curious intensity to a young actress, and his
wife, after attempting to laugh at the situation in a dignified and indifferent
way, broke down entirely and resorted to flank attacks— —at intervals she appeared
suddenly at his side like an angry diamond, and hissed: “You promised!” into his ear.
The reluctance to go home was not confined to wayward men. The hall was at
present occupied by two deplorably sober men in their highly indignant wives. The
wives were sympathizing with each other and slightly raised voices. “Whenever he
sees I’m having a good time he wants to go home.” “Never heard anything so selfish
in my life.” “We’re always the first ones
to leave.” “So are we.” “Well, we’re almost the last tonight,” said one of the men
sheepishly. “The orchestra left half an hour ago.” In spite of the wives’ agreement
that such malevolence was beyond credibility, the dispute ended in a short
struggle, and both wives were lifted, kicking, into the night.
As I waited for my hat in the hall the door the library opened in Jordan Baker
and Gatsby came out together. He was saying some last word to her, but the
eagerness in his manner tightened abruptly into formality as several
people approached him to say goodbye.
Jordan’s party were calling impatiently to her from the porch, but she lingered
for a moment to shake hands.
“I’ve just heard the most amazing thing,” she whispered. “How long were we in there?”
“Why, about an hour.” “It was… simply amazing,” she repeated abstractedly. “But I swore I
wouldn’t tell it and here I am tantalizing you.” She yawned gracefully in my face.
“Please come and see me… Phone book… Under the name Miss Sigourney Howard… My aunt…”
She was hurrying off as she talked— —her brown hand waved a jaunty salute as she
melted into her party at the door.
Rather ashamed that on my first appearance I'd stayed so late, I joined
the last of Gatsby’s guests, who were clustered around him.
I wanted to explain that I’d hunted for him early in the evening and to
apologize for not having known him in the garden.
“Don’t mention it,” he enjoined me eagerly.
“Don’t give it another thought, old sport.” The familiar expression held no more
familiarity than the hand which reassuringly brushed my shoulder. “And
don’t forget we’re going up in the hydroplane tomorrow morning, at nine o’clock.”
Then the butler, behind his shoulder: “Philadelphia wants you on the phone, sir
alright in a minute. Tell them I’ll be right there… Good night.” “Good night.” “Good night.”
He smiled— —and suddenly there seemed to be a pleasant significance in having
been among the last to go, as if he had desired it all the time.
“Good night, old sport… Good night.” But as I walked down the steps I saw
that the evening was not quite over 50 feet from the door a dozen headlights
illuminated a bizarre and tumultuous scene. In the ditch beside the road, right
side up, but violently shorn of one wheel, rested a new Coop which had left
Gatsby’s drive not two minutes before.
The sharp jut of a wall accounted for the detachment of the wheel, which was
now getting considerable attention from half a dozen curious chauffeurs. However,
as they had left their cars blocking the road, a harsh, discordant din from those
in the rear had been audible for some time, and added to the already violent
confusion of the scene. A man in a long duster had dismounted from the wreck and
now stood in the middle of the road, looking from the car to the tire and
from the tire to the observers in a pleasant, puzzled way.
“See!” he explained. “It went in the ditch.” The fact was infinitely astonishing to
him, and I recognized first the unusual quality of wonder, and then the man— —it
was in the late patron of Gatsby’s library.
“How’d it happen?” He shrugged his shoulders.
“I know nothing whatever about mechanics,” he said decisively. “But how did it happen?
Did you run into the wall?” “Don’t ask me,” said Owl Eyes, washing his hands of the
whole matter. “I know very little about driving— —next to nothing. It happened, and
that’s all I know.” “Well, if you’re a poor driver you ought
to try driving at night.” “But I wasn’t even trying,” he explained indignantly, “I
wasn’t even trying.” An odd hush fell upon the bystanders. “Do
you want to commit suicide?” “You’re lucky it was just a wheel! A bad driver and not
even trying You don’t understand explain the criminal. “I wasn’t driving. There’s
another man in the car shock that followed this declaration found voice in a sustained ah as the
door of the coop swung slowly open. The crowd— —it was now a crowd— —stepped back
involuntarily, and when the door had opened why there was a ghostly pause.
Then, very gradually, part by part, a pale, dangling individual stepped out of the
wreck, pawing tentatively at the ground with a large uncertain dancing shoe.
Blinded by the glare of the headlights and confused by the incessant groaning
of the horns, the apparition stood swaying for a moment before he perceived
the man in the duster what's the matter?” he inquired calmly. “Did we run out of gas?” “Look!”
Half a dozen fingers pointed at the amputated wheel— —he stared at it for a
moment, and then looked upward as though he suspected that it had dropped from
the sky. “It came off,” someone explained. He nodded. “At first I didn't notice we’d
stopped.” A pause. Then, taking a long breath and straightening his shoulders,
he remarked in a determined voice wonder if he'll tell me whether there's a gas
line station wonder if and tell me where is a gas line station?” At least a dozen
men, some of them little better off than he was, explained to him that wheel and
car were no longer joined by any physical bond.
“Back out,” he suggested after a moment. “Put her in reverse.” “But the wheels off!” He
hesitated. “No harm in trying,” he said. The caterwauling horns had reached a
crescendo and I turned away and cut across the lawn toward home.
I glanced back once.
A wafer of a moon was shining over Gatsby’s house, making the night fine as
before, and surviving the laughter and the sound of his still glowing garden.
A sudden emptiness seemed to flow now from the windows and the great doors,
endowing with complete isolation the figure of the host, who stood on the
porch, his hand up in a formal gesture of farewell. Reading over what I've written
so far, I see I've given the impression that the events of three nights several
weeks apart were all that absorbed me.
On the contrary, they were merely casual events in a crowded summer, and, until
much later, they absorbed me infinitely less than my personal affairs. Most of
the time I worked. In the early morning the sun through my shadow westward as I
hurried down the white chasms of lower New York to the Probity Trust.
I knew the other clerks and young Bond salesman by their first names, and lunged
with them in dark, crowded restaurants on little Pigs sausages and mashed potatoes and coffee.
I even had a short affair with a girl who lived in Jersey City and worked in
the accounting department, but her brother began throwing mean looks in my
direction, so when she went on her vacation in July I let it blow quietly
away. I took dinner usually at the Yale Club— —for some reason it was the
gloomiest event of my day— —and then I went upstairs to the library and studied
investments and securities for a conscientious hour they were generally a
few rioters around, but they never came into the library, so it was a good place
to work. After that, if the night was mellow, I strolled down Madison Avenue
past the old Murray Hill Hotel, and over 33rd Street to the Pennsylvania Station.
I began to like New York, the racy, adventurous feel of it at night, and the
satisfaction that the constant flicker of men and women and machines gives to
the restless eye. I liked to walk up Fifth Avenue and pick out romantic women
from the crowd and imagine that in a few minutes I was going to enter into their
lives, and no one would ever know or disapprove. Sometimes, in my mind, I
followed them to their apartments on the corners of hidden streets, and they
turned and smiled back at me before they faded through a door into warm darkness.
At the enchanted metropolitan twilight I felt a haunting loneliness sometimes, and
felt it in others— —poor young clerks who loitered in front of windows waiting
until it was time for a solitary restaurant dinner— —young clerks in the
dusk, wasting the most poignant moments of night and life. Again at eight o’clock,
when the dark lanes of the 40s were five deep with throbbing taxi cabs bound for
the Theater district, I felt a sinking in my heart. Forms leaned together in the
taxis as they waited, and voices sang, and there was laughter from unheard jokes,
and lighted cigarettes outlined unintelligible gestures inside. Imagining
that I, too, was hurrying toward gaity and sharing their intimate excitement, I
wished them well.
For a while I lost sight of Jordan Baker, and then in mid-summer I found her again.
At first I was flattered to go places with her, because she was a golf champion,
and everyone knew her name. Then it was something more.
I wasn’t actually in love, but I felt a sort of tender curiosity. The bored
haughty face that she turned to the world concealed something— —most
affections conceal something eventually, even though they don’t in the beginning—
—and one day I found what it was. When we were on a house party together up in
Warwick, she left a borrowed car out in the rain with the top down, and then lied
about it— —and suddenly I remembered the story about her that had eluded me that
night at daisies At her first big golf tournament there was a row that nearly
reached the newspapers— —a suggestion that she had moved her ball from a bad lie in
the semi-final round. The thing approached the proportions of a scandal—
—then died away. A caddy retracted his statement, and the only other witness
admitted that he might have been mistaken. The incident and the name had
remained together in my mind.
Jordan Baker instinctively avoided clever, shrewd men, and now I saw that this was because she
felt safer on a plane where any Divergent from a code would be thought impossible.
She was incurably dishonest. She wasn’t able to endure being at a disadvantage
and, given this unwillingness, I suppose she had begun dealing in subterfuges
when she was very young in order to keep that cool, insolent smile turned to the world
and yet satisfy the demands of her hard, jaunty body.
It made no difference to me. Dishonesty in a woman is a thing you never blame deeply—
—I was casually sorry, and then I forgot.
It was on that same house party that we had a curious conversation about driving a car.
It started because she passed so close to some workmen that our fender flicked
a button on one man’s coat.
“You’re a rotten driver,” I protested.
“Either you ought to be more careful were you ought to drive at all.” “I am careful.”
“No, you’re not.” “Well, other people are,” she said lightly.
“What’s that got to do with it?” “They’ll keep out of my way,” she insisted.
“It takes two to make an accident.” “Suppose you met somebody just as careless as yourself.”
“I hope I never will,” she answered.
“I hate careless people.
That’s why I like you.” Her gray Sun's strained eyes stared straight ahead,
but she had deliberately shifted our relations, and for a moment I thought I loved her.
But I'm slow thinking and full of interior rules that act as breaks on my desires,
and I knew that first I had to get myself definitely out of that tangle back home
I've been writing letters once a week and signing them: “Love neck and all I
could think of was how, when that certain girl played tennis, a faint mustache of perspiration
appeared on her upper lip.
Nevertheless there was a vague understanding that had to be tactfully
broken off before I was free.
Everyone suspects himself of at least one of the cardinal virtues, and this is mine:
I am one of the few honest people that I have ever known